This video is sponsored by the visual
learning app Imprint. Discover
life-changing insights from philosophy,
science, and more. Get a free 7-day
trial and 25% off using my link in the
description.
Simultaneously one of the most cynical
[music] and hopeful thinkers in history,
Bla1 Pascal was a scientific genius
brought to spiritual extremes, [music] a
morbidly sensitive, neurotic-like mind
with the eloquence of a poet, and a
theologian who saw God, reason, and
meaning, fear, misery, and hope, all in
a strange dance where they never quite
touch, but always move in lock step,
striving toward a display of redemption.
Pascal was born in 1623 in Claremont
Feron, France. As a young boy, he very
quickly had many reasons to feel the
despair etched into [music] human
existence. His mother died when he was
just 3 years old. He was frequently ill,
dealing with chronic issues like
digestive and abdominal disorders,
migraines, and neurological attacks, as
well as many other symptoms like
heightened sensitivity, [music] pain,
and fatigue. Largely because of these
health issues, he experienced a very
constrained early social life. From
within this vortex of social isolation,
a sickly body and an awareness of the
transients of life found in the empty
space left by his mother. Pascal looked
out at the world and saw all this
detail, absurdity, and horror through
the eyes of a genius. By an early age,
it was clear that Pascal was a prodigy
in math and science. By just 12 years
old, he had worked out Uklid's first 32
geometric propositions completely on his
own. By age 16, he had developed a
theorem in geometry still known today as
Pascal's theorem. By his 20s, he had
constructed what would become the first
mechanical calculator, formulated the
principles behind the hydraulic press
and syringe, helped invent what would
become modern probability theory, and
assisted in establishing Paris's [music]
first public transport system. He was
fully on his way to becoming a major
scientist and mathematician of the
scientific revolution. That is until
[music] things took a very strange and
unexpected turn.
By his early 30s, Pascal had essentially
given up on math and science. Instead,
his focus turned almost entirely toward
religious and philosophical matters.
This shift was likely partly brought on
by his health challenges, which had only
continued to get worse. Far more
significantly, however, it appears to
have been triggered by a sudden,
bizarre, and powerful religious
experience he had at age 31, which would
come to be referred to as the night of
fire. While likely alone at home one
night, a sudden, violent, visceral
experience of fire, peace, joy,
certainty, and God overwhelmed Pascal.
[music] It was, according to him,
something beyond all reason, language,
and philosophy, an intellectual rebirth,
a descent into a kind of spiritual
madness, or both, depending on who you
ask. Soon after, Pascal began to write a
book. His intention was to defend
Christianity and bring readers to God.
At age 39, however, Pascal died from his
lifelong escalating battle with poor
health. The precise cause never fully
being determined. He never managed to
finish the book. Instead, [music] the
notes, ideas, and arguments that he left
behind during the early development
process [music] were collected and
pieced together, forming what is now
known as Pon, an apheristic style book
exploring nearly all aspects of the
human condition. Somewhat ironically,
Pon would go on to become far more
famous for its secular philosophical
insights than its religious defenses.
Pascal originally intended the book to
be divided into two parts. The first
part was supposed to be a diagnosis of
the human condition as an ailment. The
second part was supposed to function as
a prescription of Christianity as the
treatment. The surviving Pon, however,
lays out into several sections,
primarily an exploration of existential
despair, the human longing for hope and
meaning, the primary modes of thought
and reason, and attempts at a
theological defense for redemption. In
the work, Pascal covers just about
everything that is terrible about human
existence. From corruption to anxiety to
hubris to our frenzy for distraction
from ourselves and our reality. With the
weight of each word in line, Pascal
pulls us down from the surface of our
day-to-day lives and into the underbelly
of existence. Down here, he shows us the
despair, the depravity, and the
vacantness of humanity, a museum of
existential horrors. Pascal argued that
people generally avoid this museum at
all costs. Nearly everything we do is to
add more layers and distance between us
and this realm. All of man's unhappiness
comes from his inability to stay
peacefully alone in his room. He wrote,
"The Museum of Existential Horrors does
not contain skulls or vats of blood, but
merely the emptiness of space and time
to sit with ourselves and our thoughts."
Pascal writes, "So who does not see it
apart from young people whose lives are
all noise, diversions and thoughts for
the future? But take away their
diversion and you will see them bored to
extinction. Then they feel their nullity
without recognizing it. For nothing
could be more wretched than to be
intolerably depressed as soon as one
[music] is reduced to introspection with
no means of diversion."
Crucially for Pascal, the initial point
of facing up to the wretchedness and
barrenness of our condition is to know
ourselves fully and accurately. An
accurate self-conception is the first
step to greatness and salvation. He
writes, "Man's greatness comes from
knowing that he is wretched. A tree does
not know it is wretched. Thus, it is
wretched to know that one is wretched.
But there is greatness in knowing one is
wretched." We overcome ourselves and our
condition not by being something other
than what we are but by recognizing what
we are and working toward living well
within this condition. For Pascal, we
live well within this condition through
God. In the words of historian Michael
Sigru, Pascal's idea is you have to make
individuals fear for the good of their
soul. Make them fear the possibility
that they're not going to get what
religion might offer to them. You have
to show them how wretched they are.
Pascal wants to inspire in the reader a
kind of terror, a kind of morbid hatred
of the nuts and bolts, tables and
chairs, facts of the human condition.
Though explicitly for Pascal, the cure
to the ailment of being is God, more
fundamentally, it is the search for God.
And deeper than that, arguably it is
really the search for a cure. Deviating
from Pascal, this cure need not be God.
It need not be religious. It need not
even be spiritual in the traditional
sense. Arguably, God is merely a
stand-in [music] for transcendent hope
and meaning beyond reason. And perhaps
that could be found in reason or meaning
or hope itself. It can be [music]
existence itself.
One of Pascal's most famous arguments is
what is known as Pascal's wager. In
short, the argument claims it is a
better bet to believe in God than to
not. [music] This is because if you're
right and God exists, you gain eternal
salvation in heaven. If you're wrong,
you only lose some finite earthly
pleasures, which for Pascal are
ultimately trivial relative to the
stakes. And even if God doesn't exist,
Pascal argues that living as if he does
leads to a more stable and meaningful
inner experience [music] here on Earth.
He doesn't see this argument as proof of
God, but rather proof that it's worth
searching for him, the hope in striving
toward him. However, could not the same
fundamental argument and wager be
applied to the [music] search for the
value and meaning of earthly human
existence without belief in God? Could
not a compelling wager look like this?
It is a better bet to believe this life
is meaningful, valuable, and good in and
of itself, and that this life is all
there is. Because if you're right, then
you win the reward of experiencing the
only time you have as positively as
possible. Not with disdain or dejection,
not with the hope in holding out for
something else, but with the embrace and
love for this right now. If you're wrong
and there is some kind of afterlife,
then you also gain the upside of
whatever that may be, which surely no
human can know enough about to predict
the terms of. Likewise, this is not
proof that human existence is meaningful
and worthwhile in and of itself, but it
is proof [music] that it is worth
striving toward this belief, toward
creating its truth.
Pascal wanted to compel us toward God by
showing us how terrible our condition
is. But in the process, arguably what he
really showed us is how strong we are or
can be. He shows us that everything
isn't and won't be okay. And yet somehow
we can and continue to endure. Whether
through God or something God-shaped, we
can create and imagine worlds and ideas
worth living in. The morbid absurdities
of our condition, the frenzied nature of
our lives, our anxieties, our
depravities, it is all real. It is all
in everyone. But we can survive these
qualities and the knowledge thereof and
still be compelled to seek redemption
regardless of any religious belief. This
profound impulse and ability is embodied
in Pon and it is found in every instance
where the human psyche confronts the
hardship of existence and continues
forward overcoming, transmuting [music]
and justifying.
In the end, Pascal's incomplete book
beautifully [music] and poignantly
completed his life's work. The
apheristic structure is a nod to the
fragmented nature of thought, a
long-standing literary format in
philosophy, and the disordered
progression of his life. and it is
likely what ultimately contributed to
its large-scale enduring readability and
success. His work and legacy have and
continue to show us that no matter how
pessimistic we might be, no matter how
bad [music] things might seem, the
striving for hope, the foraging for
answers and meaning and redemption
[music] endures within us whether we
like it or not, whether it makes any
sense or not. History is a constant
reinvention of hope and meaning in all
forms, mythological, technological, and
philosophical. We keep questioning,
answering, [music] building, destroying.
Questioning, answering, building,
destroying. We can't help ourselves from
helping ourselves.
Pascal had a very eclectic range of
[music] interests: math, science,
philosophy, theology, and psychology.
[music] As his life shows, following the
full scope of our curiosities can lead
us to so many places, often unexpected
ones. This video sponsor, Imprint, turns
following your interests, curiosities,
and goals into a beautiful, immersive,
and engaging process. Imprint recognizes
that we learn best through [music]
intuitive experiences, not bland
information. And so, through beautifully
animated and gamified courses and
bite-sized lessons, [music] Imprint
distills ideas from subjects like
philosophy, psychology, science,
finance, and [music] more into something
you can see and feel. Visualized
insights you can seamlessly scroll
through. With imprint, learning happens
anywhere, [music] anytime, fitting
within and building upon how you already
use technology every day. It becomes
[music] fun, exciting, and habitual.
Whether you want to explore schools of
thought like epicurionism, the nature of
time, the psychology of money, or any
other topic, Imprint lets you easily
dive into the subjects you care about,
keeping you focused on what matters,
digging into the world, the mind, and
yourself. With over 50,000 five-star
reviews on the App Store and Google
Play, and winning awards like Google's
App of the Year and Apple's Essential
Education app, Imprint has proven that
it is an incredible way to uncover
insights that make a difference. Use my
link in the description to sign up for
Imprint, and you'll receive a 7-day free
trial and 25% off [music] your annual
premium membership.
And of course, as always, thank you so
much for watching in general, and see
you next video.